We started with various types of practices
हमने विभिन्न प्रकार की प्रथाओं के साथ
of Ashtanga Yogas, eightfold yogas, with a guru
अष्टांग योग की शुरुआत की, अष्टांग योग, एक गुरु के साथ
and one had to go through lots of hardships.
और व्यक्ति को बहुत कठिनाइयों से गुजरना पड़ता था।
Nobody who was married, was allowed into that Ashtanga yoga and they had to
कोई भी जो शादीशुदा था, उसे अनुमति नहीं थी उस अष्टांग योग में जाने की और उन्हें
give up their families, give up their relationships.
अपने परिवारों का त्याग, रिश्तेदारियों का त्याग करना पड़ता था।
They had to become absolutely [ASIDE - Just a minute] -
उन्हें बिल्कुल बनना पड़ता था [एक ओर - बस एक मिनट] -
absolutely without any attachments to go to a guru.
बिल्कुल बिना किसी बंधन के, गुरु के पास जाने के लिए।
All their property, all their possessions were given up -
उन्हें अपनी सारी संपत्ति, अपना सारा स्वामित्व त्याग कर देना होता था -
not to the guru, as is done in modern times, but given away -
गुरु को नहीं, जैसा कि आधुनिक समय में किया जाता है, लेकिन दे दिया जाता था -
and this was called as Yoga.
और इसे योग कहा जाता था।
The another style was called as Sankhya. Sankhya is where
दूसरी शैली को सांख्य कहा जाता था। सांख्य वह है जहाँ
all your life you have to gather things with detachment
आपको अपने सारे जीवन विरक्ति से चीजें इकट्ठी करनी होतीं थीं
and then to distribute them completely
और फिर उन्हें पूरी तरह से वितरित करना होता था
and take to a guru, in a way completely surrender, and then get realization.
और गुरु की शरण में जाओ, पूरी तरह से समर्पण करो, और फिर बोध प्राप्त करो।
Sankhya is the right sided - sorry - Sankhya was the left-sided behavior
सांख्य दाहिनी ओर है - क्षमा करें - सांख्य वामपंथी व्यवहार था
and the yoga was the right-sided where the Gayatri mantra was used was the Sankhya.
और योग दाहिनी ओर था, जहाँ सांख्य में गायत्री मंत्र का प्रयोग किया जाता था।
Because they were left-sided, they used to use Gayatri mantra.
क्योंकि वे बाएं तरफा थे, वे गायत्री मंत्र का प्रयोग करते थे।
They went so much to the left side, that is to gather things, to gather possessions,
वे  इतना बाईं ओर चले जाते थे, कि सामान इकट्ठा करना है, संपत्ति इकट्ठी करनी है,
to gather properties, to gather all kinds of friends and relations and societies,
ज़मीन-जायदाद इकट्ठी करनी है, सब प्रकार के मित्रों और संबंधों और समाजों को इकट्ठा करना है,
that they were afraid that they may be completely lost into all those things.
कि उन्हें भय था कि कहीं वह पूरी तरह से उन सभी चीजों में खो सकते हैं।
They would go to Gayatri, the mantra of Gayatri, which teaches you the
गायत्री के पास जाते थे, गायत्री का मंत्र, जो आपको सिखाता है
essences of all our chakras, the centres.
हमारे सभी चक्रों, केंद्रों का सार।
So the people who did Sankhya were sort of not so much respected as spiritual people
तो सांख्य करने वाले लोग, एक प्रकार से, आध्यात्मिक लोगों के रूप में इतना सम्मानित नहीं थे
because they thought these are all involved into worldly things and worldly possessions
क्योंकि उन्हें लगा कि ये सब सांसारिक चीजों और सांसारिक संपत्तियों में
and worldly happenings, so they were regarded as something secondary.
और सांसारिक घटनाओं में लिप्त/शामिल हैं, इसलिए उन्हें कुछ गौण माना जाता था।
Or those who were yogis of the gurus were regarded higher because they had already
या जो गुरुओं के योगी थे उन्हें उच्च माना जाता था क्योंकि उन्होंने पहले से ही
given up everything and they have gone to a guru, giving up all the things that they have.
सब कुछ छोड़ दिया और अपना सब कुछ त्याग कर वे गुरु के पास चले गए थे।
But here, these gurus had a problem within themselves
लेकिन यहाँ, अपने आप में इन गुरुओं को एक समस्या थी
because they found that those who came to them gave up everything no doubt,
क्योंकि उन्होंने पाया कि जो लोग, निःसंदेह सब कुछ त्याग कर उनके पास आये थे,
but still there was lurking attachments. In their own ashramas they found
लेकिन फिर भी उनमें गुप्त लगाव था। उन्होंने अपने आश्रमों में पाया कि
these people had their own attachments to things. Though outwardly they had given up
इन लोगों को अपनी चीज़ों के प्रति लगाव था। हालांकि बाहरी तौर पर उन्होंने सब कुछ छोड़ दिया था
but inside they had not given up. So they were still sticking on to these ideas
लेकिन आंतरिक रूप से उन्होंने नहीं त्यागा था। इसलिए वे अभी भी इन विचारों से ग्रस्त थे
that, uh, "Oh it's alright but still we can have little things like that,
कि, "ओह, यह ठीक है लेकिन फिर भी हमारे पास इस तरह की छोटी चीजें हो सकती हैं,
doesn't matter," like that, there was little compromises going on.
कोई फर्क नहीं पड़ता," उस तरह, वहाँ छोटे-छोटे समझौते हो रहे थे।
Like as we have here nunneries and all that.
जैसे हमारे यहाँ भिक्षुणियाँ/ननरीज़ हैं और वो सब।
So both, in a way, were artificial.
तो, एक तरह से, दोनों कृत्रिम थे।
The one side is the Sankhyas, were trying to ascend with all the luggage they were carrying
एक तरफ सांख्य हैं, जो अपना बोझा ले कर चढ़ने का प्रयत्न कर रहे थे,
and another were trying to descend with all the ambitions of ascend.
और दूसरे उतरने की कोशिश कर रहे थे उत्थान की सभी महत्वाकांक्षाओं के साथ।
So it was a very funny thing in every aspect, in both these styles of yoga.
तो, योग की इन दोनों शैलियों में, यह एक बहुत ही मजेदार/अज़ीब पहलू था।